Finding Aid for Gargoyle records, 1910-2012
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Gargoyle records 1910-2012 1993-1999
Gargoyle (Organization)
3 linear feet and 1 outsize box
0737 Bimu 2
The Gargoyle, a University of Michigan humor magazine, was first published in 1909. The collection includes correspondence, ephemera, photographs, reminiscences from Gargoyle staff members, and some original artwork.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Materials received from multiple donors, including John Dobbertin, Jr. (donor no. 332 ), Doris A. Smith (donor no. 8686 ), Norman Williamson (donor no. 84482 ), Beverly Burlingame (donor no. 9735 ), Student Publications Office (donor no. 332 ), and the Board for Student Publications (donor no. 1509 ). 332
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research without restriction.
The Gargoyle, a University of Michigan humor magazine regulated by the Board for Student Publications, was first published in 1909. Gargoyle began as a part humor and part fine arts publication. Gargoyle is still published at the University of Michigan. For a more in-depth discussion of the history of Gargoyle including reminiscences and first-hand accounts from former Gargoyle staff members, researchers should consult the book Gargoyle The University of Michigan Humor Magazine Laughs at the 20th Century, compiled and edited by John Dobbertin, Jr. in 1999.
The collection includes various materials and papers from former staff members, primarily from John Dobbertin, Jr., Gargoyle editor from 1962-1964. Dobbertin organized many reunions and served as a clearing house for Gargoyle ephemera. Materials include correspondence, ephemera, photographs, reminiscences from Gargoyle staff members, printed material, and original artwork.
The collection has been divided into two series: Manuscript Materials and Printed Materials.
Subjects:
University of Michigan--Students--Periodicals.; College wit and humor.; University of Michigan--Alumni and alumnae.; University of Michigan--Students--Social Life.
Contributors:
Dobbertin, John.; Hodge, Max.; Schulz, Charles M.; Smith, Doris Ann.; Zatret, Phil.
Genre/Form:
Magazine covers.; Periodical Illustrations.; Posters.; Cartoons (humorous images)
- Manuscript Materials, 1937-2012
  The Manuscript Materials (0.8 linear feet, 1937-2012) include correspondence, ephemera, photographs, reminiscences from Gargoyle staff members, and original artwork. Researchers will find original Gargoyle artwork (cover art and other illustrations) by former art editors, Doris A. Smith, Max Hodge, Phil Zaret, and others as well as an original cartoon by "Peanuts" cartoonist Charles Schulz created for an issue of the Gargoyle marking its revival in 1962. Photographs include the Gargoyle 1993 reunion and miscellaneous photographs of Gargoyle staff in the 1930s and 1940s. The correspondence contains letters mainly addressed to John Dobbertin, Jr. from former Gargoyle staff, including former editor George Quick. The correspondence also contains letters from Arthur Miller and Charles Schulz. The reminiscences consist of various recollections of former staff members on life at Gargoyle during their time at the University of Michigan compiled by Dobbertin to be used in the Gargoyle book. The collection also includes two printing plates, both Max Hodge designs, one for the January 1938 cover and the other for a "Michigarg" board game (color prints of the board game can be found in the oversize folder).
  - Printing Plates, 1937-1938 (Box 1)
  - Promotional posters (Box 1)
  - Artwork, 1936-1969, 1993 (Box 1)
  - 1962 Revival Issue cover signed by attendees at 100th reunion, 2007 (Box 1)
  - Artwork, 1936-1969, 1993-2003, 2009 (Box 2)
  - Clippings (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1962, 1993-2001, 2009-2012, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Ephemera, 1939-1993 (Box 2)
  - Layouts, [1966 ?] (Box 2)
  - "Order of the Gargoyle," 1997 (Box 2)
  - Photographs, 1937-1993, 1999, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Reminiscences, 1993-1999, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Reunion, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Staff members
    - Paul Showers, 1999 (Box 2)
    - Doris A. Smith, 1960s-1997 (Box 2)
    - Norm Williamson, 2001-2002 (Box 2)
- Printed Materials, 1910-2006
  The Printed Materials (2.2 linear feet, 1910-2006) include various published items including a copy of Gargoyle The University of Michigan Humor Magazine Laughs at the 20th Century, the Gargalum newsletter, and duplicate issues of the Gargoyle. For a more complete set of the Gargoyle, researchers should consult the separately cataloged issues in MIRLYN.
  - Gargalum (newsletter), 1994-2007 (Box 2)
  - Gargoyle The University of Michigan Humor Magazine Laughs at the 20th Century, 1999 (Box 2)
  - Gargoyle (duplicate issues)
    - Bound copy of 1930-1931 issues (Box 2)
      (Paul Showers copy)
    - 1910-1947 (Box 3)
    - 1948-2006 (Box 4)
Relatd Material
Additional Gargoyle materials can be found in other collections at the Bentley, including the Board for Student Publications records and the Paul Showers papers. The Board for Student Publications includes some Gargoyle financial and administrative material (1937-1951). The Paul Showers papers contain writings and correspondence when Showers was on the Gargoyle staff in the 1930s. The Bentley also owns issues of the Baby Gargoyle, a separate annual "pocket-sized" publication produced by Gargoyle.